Finding Aid for the Edwin Mims Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
- Autobiography
  - Class Lectures (2 folders) (Box 18)
  - Clippings, misc. published material collected by Mims: (arranged chronologically) (Box 18)
    ca. July, 1896, “Liberty, Justice, Equality,” leaflet in support of the Bentley-Southgate Ticket.
    July 7, 1900, “The Ticket and Platform for the Observer’s Position,” (no newspaper title).
    May 15, 1909, The Outlook, Vol. 92, No. 3. (entire issue intact).
    ca. June, 1915, “Dedicated to Chancellor St. Judas and The Trustees of Kirknegiebilt University. With Apologies to Mr. G. Byron” (no source listed).
  - “Woodrow Wilson’s Place in History,” by Jan Christian Smuts. (no journal title)., ca. 1921 (Box 18)
  - “The Impact of Science Upon Society,” by Sir Josiah Stamp, British Association for the Advancement of Society - Blackpool, 1936; The Presidential Address., 1936 (Box 18)
  - “Parliament” (News Reviews), The Times, London., March 27, 1936 (Box 18)
  - “The Moderate Nan Is At A Discount,” Public Opinion, Address by Lord Tweedsmuir, Governor-General of Canada., Jan. 8, 1937 (Box 18)
  - “Death of Mr. Edward Garnett,” The Manchester Guardian (?)., Feb. 26, 1939 (Box 18)
  - “‘Sawney Webb’,” by William R. Webb, Jr. Reprinted from April Number of The Sewanee Review., 1942 (Box 18)
  - The Key Reporter - The Phi Beta Kappa News Magazine, Vol. XX, No. 2., Feb. 1955 (Box 18)
  - “The South and Integration:’South’s Worst Qualities Have Come Out’,” An interview with Mark Ethridge, Publisher Louisville Courier Journal, The Nashville Banner., March 13, 1956 (Box 18)
  - “The Middle of the Road - Where It Leads,” by Richard M. Weaver, Human Events., March 24, 1956 (Box 18)
  - “We Will Not Close Our Schools,” by Jonathan Daniels, North Carolina Education., Jan. 1959 (Box 18)
- N.D.’S
  - “As Calhoun Lay Dying,” by Ralph McGill. (Box 18)
  - “Do Reds Make Blues Blue?,” by Dudley Meads MacKegg. (Box 18)
  - “Lux Mundi,” Incidentally (column) by Nell Battle Lewis (Box 18)
  - “The Institute and Our Industrial Development,” by Henry M. Robinson. (Box 18)
  - “Loncoln: A Southern View,” by Archibald Rutledge, The Reviewer. (Box 18)
  - “Professor Gilbert Murray, Seventieth Birthday Honoured,” The Times, London. (Box 18)
  - “Southern Literature,” by W.M. Baskerville. (Box 18)
  - “The Two Conservatisms,” by Clinton Rossiter. (Box 18)
  - “What Is ‘The Last Death’?,” by Ralph McGill. (Box 18)
  - Also 6 titled fragments, and misc. untitled fragments not indexed. (Box 18)
  - Comments - by others about Mims’ lecture tours (Phi Beta Kappa, Carnegie, etc.) (Box 19)
  - French Diary (Box 19)
  - Lecture Programs, Course Syllabus (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “Anti-Lynching Movement” (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “Anti-Lynching Petition” (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “Atticus G. Haygood: Liberal Spokesman of the New South” (Box 19)
  - Mss. - Autobiographical fragment - education in the South, etc. (Box 19)
  - Mss. - Autogiographical fragment - regions of U.S. (Box 19)
  - Mss. - Autobiographical fragment - South Atlantic Quarterly (Box 19)
  - Mss. - Book Reviews (Box 19)
  - Mss. -“Booker Washington in Boston” (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “Bright Eyes” (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “Chancellor Kirkland and Vanderbilt University” (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “Ellen Glasgow: Social Historian of Virginia” (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “French Literary Influence on England and U.S. (incomplete) (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “A Group of Southern Historians” (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “Henry Grady” (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “In Search of the United States” + Review (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “A Man and a Book” (Atticus G. Haygood) (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “The Mid-Victorians” (Box 19)
  - Mss. - Milton (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “Mr. Menoken and Mr. Sherman...” (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “Modern Education and Religion” (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “New Light on an Old Problem” (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “Obligations of American Life”, “Options”, “Peace and World Order”, “Thomas Nelson Page - A Reminiscence” (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “Personal Experiences with Southern Authors” (Box 19)
  - Mss. - (Professor Gildersleeve) (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “A Reconsideration of Early Southern Literature” (Box 19)
  - Mss. - “The Romance and Realism of the West” (Box 20)
  - Mss. - “Samuel Johnson” (Box 20)
  - Mss. - “A Semi-Centennial Survey of North Carolina’s Intellectual Progress” (Box 20)
  - Mss. - “Sidney Lanier and Higher Education” (Box 20)
  - Mss. - “Sixty Years in the Classroom” (Box 20)
  - Mss.- “The South Realizing Itself” (“Hartsville and Its Lesson”) (Box 20)
  - Mss. - “Southern Conference for Education in the South” (Box 20)
  - Mss. - (Southern “Profiles in Courage”) (incomplete) (Box 20)
  - Mss. -“Southern Rebels of Another Type” (Box 20)
  - Mss. - “A Tramp Trip through the Smoky Mountains” (Box 20)
  - Mss. - “The Voice of the Negro” (Box 20)
  - Misc. Lists and Programs (C.S. Johnson Funeral) (Box 20)
  - Misc. Ms. Material - typed original (autobiographical) (Box 20)
  - Misc. Ms. Material - typed carbons (autobiographical) (Box 20)
  - Misc. Ms. Material typed originals (general) (4 folders) (Box 20)
  - Misc. Ms. Material - typed carbons (general) (Box 20)
  - Misc. Notes, Mss. etc. (9 folders) (Box 21)
  - Notes on Peace (Box 21)
  - Notes on Rev. J. Galluchat (Box 21)
  - Pamphlets - by others (Box 21)
  - Passport, Photograph (latter of Hiram Lorson?) (Box 21)
  - Publisher’s Mtls. - Misc. (Box 22)
  - Research Notes (8 folders) (Box 22)
  - Scottish Diary (Box 22)
  - “The Southern Woman - Past and Present” (Essay by Mims in Bulletin of Randolph-Macon Woman’s College, Lynchburg, Va.) (Box 22)
  - Travel Accounts (Box 22)
  - Tributes and Biographical Mtl. (Box 22)